TheChaosLegion
I want to shine on you, and always like that dazzling sun.
I will defend you from all the darkness.
This is the truth from my heart.
If only our hearts could connect, I could get you to believe me.
Even if you can't see it now, don't lose it.
Your kindness won't be in vain.
You'll be carried aloft by the wind to somewhere that isn't here.
You'll cross the sea and cross time, and I know you'll blossom one day.
Whatever the day, I'll be there for you.
I hope I can watch over you like the sun for all time.
This is the truth from my heart.
Moribito Guardian of the Spirit
～♪
Looks like he's settled down.
（バルサ）落ち着いたようだね
さて どうしたもんかね
So...what are we
going to do about this?
ハァ…
Episode 19
Escape
I can hardly believe that
Shin-Yogo's second prince...
（ソウヤ）まさか新ヨゴの
第二皇子が―
...would end up being
the Nyunga Ro Chaga.
ニュンガ･ロ･チャガに
なるとはなあ…
If you like, we can protect him
here in the village until spring.
なんなら この村で春まで
お守りしても構わんのだが
Certain circumstances won't
allow us to accept your offer.
（トロガイ）
そうもいかん事情があってな
What should I do?
Look at what I did to the prince.
（ニムカ）どうしよう 私
皇子様に大変なことを…
（タンダ）大丈夫
君が悪いんじゃない
It's all right. It's not your fault.
あれは
俺たちの不注意だから
It happened because
we were careless, not you.
（バルサ）眠ったよ
（ニムカ）ハッ
He's asleep. It looks like the
shock has started to wear off.
（バルサ）いくらか
落ち着いたみたいだね
（タンダ）そうか
I see.
Nimka, please tell us
the rest of that story.
（バルサ）ニムカ さっきの話の
続きを聞かせておくれ
私たちも卵食いが来るってことは
分かっていた
We already knew that the
egg-eater would be coming.
The reason we
hadn't told him anything...
けど あの子に
何も話していなかったのは―
...was that we'd intended to do it after
we'd found a way to drive it off.
せめて 卵食いを退ける方法を
見つけてからと思っていたからなんだ
Please.
お願いだよ
卵食いは人に見えないし
触れないって言ってたね
You said that the egg-eater
couldn't be seen or touched.
どういうことなんだい？
What did you mean by that?
I don't know.
That's just what I was taught.
分からない
私は そう教わっただけ
ただニュンガ･ロ･チャガを
引き裂いたときには―
But she said that it
was clearly visible when...
その姿がはっきり見えたって
言ってた
...it was tearing the
Nyunga Ro Chaga apart.
大きな爪が何本も地面から
伸びてきたんだって
They said they saw many claws
coming out of the ground.
（タンダ）え？
（バルサ）爪が何本も？
Many claws?
（トロガイ）どうにも
やっかいだねえ
It sounds like trouble,
whatever it is.
ニムカよ
お前のひいばあさんは―
Nimka, did your great-grandmother
tell you anything else?
他に何か教えてくれなかったかい？
例えば 卵食いが嫌う何かを？
What the egg-eater
didn't like, for instance?
だろうな
Not surprising...
If they knew anything, they would
have tried it a hundred years ago.
そんなものがありゃ
100年前に試しとるわな
うーむ…
（ニムカ）ごめんなさい
I'm sorry. I wish I had something
encouraging to tell you...
皆さんの喜ぶ話をしてあげられれば
いいんだけど―
ニュンガ･ロ･チャガは初めから
卵食いに食べられる運命なんだって
...but she said that the Nyunga Ro
Chaga is destined to be devoured by it.
So it seems that the
Yona Ro Gai spoke the truth...
やはりヨナ･ロ･ガイが
言っていたとおりなのか
でも 卵まで食われちまったら―
But if it ate him, egg and all...
...we wouldn't have been blessed
with water like we have been.
俺たち 今頃 こうして水の恩恵を
受けることはできなかったはずですよ
That means that the egg
hatched safely a century ago.
ってことは100年前は
卵が無事かえったわけだから―
ニュンガ･ロ･チャガだって…
So why not the
Nyunga Ro Chaga also?
I think... the Nyunga Ro Chaga can
only deposit the egg here in Sagu...
（ニムカ）
多分 ニュンガ･ロ･チャガは
ラルンガに引き裂かれることで―
...by being ripped open by Rarunga.
初めてサグに卵を落とせるの
ニュンガ･ロ･イムは
サグの海で生まれて―
The say that Nyunga Ro lm
is a spirit born in Sagu's oceans...
川をさかのぼって―
...that makes its way upriver, and lives
at the bottom of Nayug's deep waters.
ナユグの深い水の底に住み着く
精霊なんだって
That's why it's necessary for
the egg to be deposited here first.
だから 一度こっちに
卵を落とす必要があるの
卵食いラルンガも―
Maybe this egg-eater Rarunga...
...is one of the forces of nature that
allows Sagu and Nayug to interact.
サグとナユグが折り合うための
摂理の１つなのかもな
だとして その生まれ出た卵は―
If that's true, how does the egg travel
from the headwaters of the Aoyumi...
どうやって青弓(あおゆみ)の水源から
海まで行くんじゃ？
...all the way to the sea
once it's deposited here?
Does it travel down
the river on its own?
勝手に川を下るのか？
It's like it says in
the rice-planting song.
それは田植え歌に
出てくるように―
ナージが卵をくわえて
海まで運んでくれるの
A nahji bird picks up the egg
in its beak and carries it to sea.
ん？ 田植え歌って
あの ナージ飛べ飛べの…
Rice-planting song?
The one that goes "Nahji, fly, fly"?
うん 田植え歌の３番は―
The third verse of the song goes...
“ナージゆけゆけ 玉さらくわえ―”
..."Go, nahji, go, take the ball in your
beak and fly up above the claws," right?
“爪のかなたに舞い上がれ”
ってなってるでしょ
あっ そんな歌あったかな？
Did the lyrics really say that?
That verse isn't sung much
around Yogo farm villages any more.
（トロガイ）そいつは
ヨゴの農村あたりじゃ―
ちょいと下品だからって―
あまり歌われなくなった一節じゃな
People thought it was a bit vulgar.
But that is certainly how we
used to sing it back in the old days.
確かに昔は そう歌ってたわい
（タンダ）じゃあ“海まで飛べば
雨降り稲穂はすくすく育つ”は―
So the line "if you fly to the sea, the
rains will fall and the seedlings will grow"...
４番だったってわけか
...was actually the
fourth verse, then?
Taken as a whole, it could mean that
a nahji will rescue Nyunga Ro lm's egg...
確かに続けるとナージが
ニュンガ･ロ･イムの卵を―
卵食いの爪から救って
海に運び―
...from the egg-eater's claws
and carry it to the sea...
精霊となって雨を降らせると
取れなくもない
...where it will grow into
a spirit and cause rain to fall.
（トロガイ）ああ…
しかし まいったね
Of all the luck... That just leaves us
with an even bigger problem.
更にやっかいな問題が出てきたわい
（タンダ）え？
（トロガイ）ナージじゃ
The nahji!
鈍いねえ お前らは
You people are
so slow to catch on...
ナージを じかに見たのは
いつが最後だ！
When was the last time
any of you saw a nahji?
あっ そういえば―
Now that you mention it...
子供のころは
空を覆い尽くすほどのナージが―
...I used to see the sky filled
with nahji as they flew south.
南に向かって渡っていくのを
見たけど―
最近は とんと
Lately, though...
They've become even rarer
since Yogo started working steel.
ヨゴ人が鉄を打つようになってからは
なおさらだ
魔よけの骨も
今は なかなか手に入らぬ貴重品
Even bones for charms against evil
spirits are hard to come by these days.
At this rate,
we might not be able to...
このままでは
小僧を守るどころか―
水の精霊すら 無事に海へ
届けることができんかもしれんぞ
...carry the water spirit safely to
the sea, let alone protect the boy.
どうやら この100年で
わしらが失ったものは―
It looks like we lost more
in the past hundred years...
...than just our customs
and oral traditions.
風習や伝承に限ったことでは
なかったようじゃな
（足音）
（タガ）お頭！
Commander!
Taga? Where is Master Shuga?
（ジン）タガか シュガ様は？
（タガ）あと６ナンのところまで
来ております
He is about six nan
away from here.
（モン）ならば あすの正午前には
トウミに着けそうだな
In that case, we should reach
Toumi sometime before noon.
（スン）はい シュガ様も
お疲れのようですが なんとか
Yes. Master Shuga appears tired,
but he should make it.
（モン）ジン お前は先に
トウミに走り―
Jin, travel on ahead to Toumi
and scout the area.
いったん 探りを入れてみろ
（ジン）分かりました
Understood.
タガ スン お前たちも行け
（タガ･スン）はっ
Taga, Sune. Go with him.
Yes, sir!
Well, then, we'll be in the
main house across the way.
（ソウヤ）では 向こうの母屋に
おりますので
（タンダ）なあ バルサ―
Look, Balsa...
さすがのお前でも
見えない相手とは戦えないよな
Not even you can fight
something that you can't see.
Plus, if Chagum has to be killed for
the egg to be deposited here in Sagu...
ましてや
卵をサグに落とすために―
チャグムは殺されなければ
ならないんだとしたら―
いっそ どこか遠くに…
（バルサ）ダメだ
...we should just run
someplace far away.
We can't. Even if
we run from here...
この場から逃げたって―
あの子が背負った運命からは
逃げられないんだよ
...there's no escaping the destiny
he's been burdened with.
Not unless we fight
to find another way.
戦って 道を切り開かないかぎりね
私も 絶対にあの子を
死なせないって約束したんだ
Also, I gave my word
that I wouldn't let him die.
必ず助けてみせる
I'll do whatever it takes to save him.
トロガイ師
何か打つ手はないのかい？
Torogai, can you think of anything?
Some way to both save Chagum and
allow the water spirit's egg to hatch?
チャグムを守ったうえで
水の精霊をかえす うまい手は
分からん
I don't know.
とりあえず 春までは
まだ時間があるんだし―
At any rate, we still have
some time before spring comes...
別の手を考えましょう
...so let's come up
with something else.
それに もし宮から
追っ手が出ているとしたら―
Besides, if the palace
has sent out pursuers...
...we can't assume
that we'll be safe here.
ここも そう安全とは思えない
なるべく早いうちに
どこかに移動しないと
We should move somewhere
else as soon as possible.
なら 狩穴(かりあな)かのう
How about Hunter's Hole, then?
あっ 確かに
Good idea. We might be able to
prepare for things if we go there too.
あそこなら いろいろ
準備も できるかもしれない
あの さっきは ごめんなさい
Um, I'm sorry about earlier.
怖い話を聞かせてしまって
I didn't mean to tell you
such a terrible story.
That's all right.
If you hadn't told us the story then...
（チャグム）いいんだ
あそこで話してくれなかったら―
俺は何も知らないままだったから
...I'd still be completely in the dark.
（チャグム）おかげで決心がついた
It's allowed me to
make up my mind.
I'm going back to the palace
by myself. Back to my mother.
俺は１人で宮に帰る
母君のところに帰るんだ
The spirit's egg has made me suffer
one terrible ordeal after another.
精霊の卵のせいで
俺ばっかり恐ろしい目に遭う
I can't take it any more.
こんなのは もう嫌だ
Wait!
待って！
I'll take you there.
連れてってあげる
え？
（ニムカ）だって怖いもんね
It's no wonder that you're scared.
いくら精霊の守り人だからって―
Even if you are the guardian of the spirit,
I'm sure you don't want to be eaten.
食べられちゃうなんて嫌だもんね
So I'll take you there.
だから 私が連れてってあげる
どうする？
村に潜入して確認するか？
What do we do? Infiltrate the
village and get confirmation?
No, people will come out to
the fields once the sun comes up.
（ジン）いや 日が昇れば
畑に人が来る
そのときに村の様子を聞く
When they do, we'll ask them
about the goings-on in the village.
短槍(たんそう)使いに気取られたくない
We don't want to alert the
spear-wielder to our presence.
（モン）シュガ様
お待ちしていました
Master Shuga, we've
been awaiting your arrival.
先にジンたちを
送り込んであります
I've sent Jin and others on ahead.
いったん休んでいただき
夜明けとともに出発いたします
Please get some rest now,
and we'll set out at dawn.
（シュガ）分かった
Very well.
But I doubt there'll be
much time for rest...
だが さして
休むわけにもいかんようだな
（ニムカの母）あの すみません
（バルサ）ん？
Excuse me.
Is Nimka still with
you in your quarters?
（ニムカの母）ニムカは
まだそちらにお邪魔していますか？
Nimka? I think she and the headman
went back to the main house last night.
（バルサ）ニムカなら 村長(むらおさ)と
夜中のうちに母屋に帰ったと思うけど
（ニムカの母）それが
先ほど寝床を見たら―
When I checked on her earlier, it
looked like her bed hadn't been slept in.
帰ってきた様子が
なかったもので
まだそちらで いろいろお話を
お聞かせしているのかと思いまして
I thought that perhaps she was telling
you more of the stories that she knows.
Moribito Guardian of the Spirit
（ニムカ）この道は
トウミの人しか知らない近道なの
Only the people of Toumi
know about this path.
ここを行けば２日で
ヤシロ村の近くまで行けるわ
If we follow this, we can reach
the Yashiro village area in two days.
（タンダ）すみません
I'm sorry. Those two left the
village, and we had no idea.
２人が出て行ったのに
まったく気付かなくて…
Well, the area is like Nimka's backyard,
so I'm not worried about her.
（ソウヤ）まあ ニムカにとっては
庭みたいなもんだから
かまわんのですが―
ニュンガ･ロ･チャガに
もしものことがあったら…
But if anything happens
to the Nyunga Ro Chaga...
（トロガイ）で いつごろ
出て行ったかは分かったのか？
So, did you figure out
when they left?
（タンダ）
ええ 明け方 犬が鳴いていたのに
気付いた人がいて―
Yes, a man said that he noticed
the dogs barking at daybreak.
どうやら そのときに
It must have been
sometime around then.
ふん まあ
バルサが追いかけたんなら―
Balsa is out looking for them...
...so I expect she'll bring
them back soon enough.
すぐに見つけて戻ってくるだろうよ
こっちは出発の準備だ
As for us, we need to
get ready to leave.
（スン）いい天気ですね
（村人）んん？
Nice day, isn't it?
（スン）驚かして すみません
I'm sorry if I startled you,
but I'd like to ask you some questions.
１つ お聞きしたいのですが―
この村に異国の女人と
ヨゴ人の男児が―
I believe that an outlander woman
and a Yogo boy are visiting the village.
訪れているはずなのですが
ご存じありませんか？
Do you know where
I might find them?
Yes, they're staying at
the village headman's place.
ああ あの人らは
村長さんとこに いるよ
村に入って一番奥の家だ
It's the furthest building
from the village entrance.
行けば すぐに分かる
You'll be able to tell
which one it is right away.
Ah, I see. There wasn't anyone else
traveling with them, was there?
そうですか
２人の他に どなたか一緒では
ありませんでしたか？
ヤクーの旦那と
そのばあさまらしい呪術師も一緒だ
There was a Yakoo man and a magic
weaver who looked like his grandmother.
But they were talking about possibly
leaving the village this morning...
でも今朝方 もう村を出るとか
出ないとか言ってたから―
どこかに
出発したかもしれませんよ？
...so they might have left for
wherever they were headed already.
This grandmother you mentioned...
（ヒョク）お前
そのばあさまというのは―
...was she an old woman about
this tall carrying a strange staff?
このくらいの背丈で
怪しげな杖をついた老婆か？
ああ そうだけど…
Yes, that's right...
Commander, we should hurry.
お頭 急ぎましょう
（モン）うむ
What's the matter?
（ニムカ）どうしたの？
（チャグム）う…
For a moment, it was like I was
somehow looking on a different landscape...
なにか 違う景色が
見えたような気がしたんだ
大丈夫？
Are you all right?
あっ バルサ
Balsa?
チャグム 村へ戻るよ
Chagum, we're going
back to the village.
I won't go.
嫌だ
どうして俺には
何も教えてくれなかったんだ？
Why did you keep
everything from me?
About the egg-eater...
About me dying...
卵食いのこと
俺が死ぬってこと
分かってたんだろう？
You knew all along, didn't you?
Yes.
The reason I kept it
from you until now...
だが 今まで黙ってたのは
確実なことが分からなかったからだ
...is because we didn't
know anything for sure.
お前を むやみに
苦しめたくなかったんだ
I didn't want to
worry you needlessly.
Liar!
（チャグム）うそだ！
バルサは俺より卵のほうが
大事なんだ
The egg is more important
to you than I am, Balsa.
それは違うよ
That's not true.
私にとっちゃ お前も卵も
大事な守るべきものなんだよ
You and the egg are both precious
things that deserve to be protected.
Deserve to be protected?
守るべきもの…
Balsa, you don't need to
worry about me any more.
バルサ 俺のことは
もういいんだ
俺は宮へ帰る
I'm returning to the palace.
You aren't my mother,
so you can't...
バルサは
俺のお母さんじゃないから
You have no idea how
I'm suffering, so you don't...
俺の苦しみなんか
分からないから…
そうか
I see. If you want to
go back that badly...
そこまで帰りたいってんなら…
Use that to kill me first.
そいつで私を倒していきな
Once I've set my mind to do something,
nothing can make me budge.
私は こうと決めたら
てこでも動かないからね
お前を宮には行かせない
I won't let you go
back to the palace.
If you insist on going
anyway, pick that up!
それでも行くってんなら
そいつを取りな
All right...
さあ そいつで私を突いてみろ！
Now then, run me through with it!
バルサが いくら強くても
巨大な爪の怪物には かなわない！
Balsa, no matter
how tough you are...
...you're no match for some
monster with gigantic claws!
I'm going back to the palace to have
Shuga and my mother protect me!
俺は宮に帰ってシュガと母君に
守ってもらうんだ！
How dare you raise a weapon
against your parent!
親に刃物向けるとは
どういう了見だ！
We're all trying our hardest
to protect you, Chagum!
（バルサ）チャグム
みんなが お前を守ろうと
頑張ってるのに―
自分１人逃げ出して どうするんだい
What were you thinking,
running off on your own?
私は お前を必ず守る
I'll protect you no matter what.
Plus, you're the
guardian of the spirit.
そして お前は
精霊の守り人なんだ
So even if you're scared...
だから怖くても最後まで
卵を守って戦うんだよ！
...you have to keep fighting to
the bitter end to protect the egg!
（チャグム）うう…
（バルサ）私の命に代えても―
Even if it costs me my life,
I won't let you die!
お前を死なせやしない！
だから私を信じておくれ！
So please, I'm asking
you to have faith in me!
（チャグム）なんで…
Why me?
なんで俺なんだ
Why does it have to be me?
村長は いるか？
Is the village headman here?
We believe the second prince of the
Shin-Yogo empire is in this village!
この村に新ヨゴ皇国の
第二皇子が訪れているはずだ
We are envoys of the mikado sent
here from Kosenkyo to retrieve him!
我らは光扇京(こうせんきょう)より皇子を
迎えに参った帝(みかど)の使いだ
今すぐ お目通り願いたい！
We request an immediate audience!
Wouldn't it be faster
to follow this river?
（トロガイ）この川沿いを行くほうが
早道なんじゃないのかい？
ですが 皇子様のことを考えると―
Yes, but if we take the
prince into consideration...
もう少し 平たんな場所を
行ったほうがよいでしょう
...a slightly more level route
would probably be better.
You have a point.
確かにな
Soya!
（村人）ソウヤさん！
今 広場に―
A man with warriors in the square
says they've been sent by the palace...
宮からの使いという方が
武人を連れて―
皇子様を迎えに来たって…
He says they've
come for the prince!
師匠！
（トロガイ）ぬかったね
Torogai?
We slipped up...
They're here already?
もう来たのかい うーむ…
I'll go and hear what
they have to say.
（ソウヤ）私が話を聞いてみましょう
You hide yourselves and wait here.
あなたたちは
ここに隠れていてください
Goodness gracious, what a treat
to have visitors from so far away!
（村長）これは これは
遠いところから
ようこそ おいでくださった
（シュガ）そなたが 村長か？
Are you the village headman?
はい そうでございます
Yes, I have that honor.
Good, that simplifies matters.
Bring out the prince at once.
（シュガ）ならば 話が早い
今すぐ ここに皇子を連れてきてくれ
I'm sorry. I'm afraid I can't do that.
それは できませんなあ
What's the meaning of this?
どういう了見だ？
You see, just as he is
precious to you as your prince...
（ソウヤ）はい それは―
あのお方が あなたたちの
大切な皇子様であると同時に―
私たちヤクーにとっても
大切な―
...to us Yakoo, he is also
the guardian of the spirit...
水の守り手を育む
精霊の守り人だからでございます
...he who nurtures the
protector of the water within him.
あの方が抱いた卵が
かえらねば―
If the egg he bears
within him fails to hatch...
この地に二度と再び
水の恵みは もたらされないのです
...these lands will never again
be blessed with water.
ですから お連れするわけには
いかないのです
So you see, this is why
we can't bring him to you.
We are also aware of these facts.
（シュガ）そのことは
我々も承知している
As such, none of us
wishes him any harm.
だから
危害を加えるつもりもないし―
むしろ 大切にお守りするために
お迎えに来たのだ
On the contrary, we are here so that
we may keep him safe and sound.
我々とて 水の恩恵を失えば
生きてはいけない
My people cannot live without
the blessings of water, either.
If your people care at all for
this land, or for Shin-Yogo...
そなたも この地と
新ヨゴ皇国を思うのであれば―
我らに精霊の卵ごと
託しては くれまいか？
...will you entrust both him
and the spirit's egg to our care?
国と言われましても―
You speak of country, but that has little
bearing on the lives of the people here.
ここに暮らす者には
あまりにも縁遠いもの
それに我々ヤクーは―
Besides, we Yakoo
have protected...
...the Nyunga Ro Chaga ourselves
for generation after generation.
代々 ニュンガ･ロ･チャガを
自分たちの手で守ってきました
100年前 この村から
ニュンガ･ロ･チャガが出たときも
Just as we did when one of our own
was the Nyunga Ro Chaga a century ago.
So I ask that you allow
us Yakoo to see to this...
ですから ここからは
我らヤクーが…
Bring out the prince while
we're still asking politely.
おとなしく頼んでいるうちに
皇子を差し出せ
Otherwise, this village
will be wiped off the map.
さもなくば この村が
地図から消えることになるぞ
（村人たちのざわめき）
（ソウヤ）それは穏やかではありませんな
That's not a very civil
tone to take, is it?
Spear-wielder! Are you listening?
短槍使い！ 聞いているか！
今度は いつぞやのようには
いかんぞ！
You won't get away
like you did before!
総力を挙げて お前を倒す！
We'll do everything in our
power to bring you down!
何が目的で皇子を
連れ回るのかは知らんが―
I don't know what your motive is,
dragging the prince around with you...
もう お前の役目は終わった！
...but your work is done!
おとなしく姿を現せ！
Come out peacefully!
（トロガイ）
うるさい小僧どもが！
Quiet, you noisy brats!
What's all this shouting about?
何を ぎゃあぎゃあ
わめいているんだい！
あの人 確か…
Wait a minute, isn't he...
わしが呪術師トロガイじゃ！
I am Torogai the magic weaver!
皇子と短槍使いは
もう ここにはおらん
The prince and the spear-wielder
are no longer here!
If you have something
to say, say it to me!
話があるなら わしが聞こう！
As I sat huddled and alone, holding back the tears on those nights...
When it felt like I was about to succumb to my doubts...
...there you were, at my side before I knew it.
It was none other than you who was there for me.
I keep wishing, "I want to be strong." I stumble and hurt myself again.
But because I have you to believe in, I can get back to my feet.
I simply want to tell my dear one, "Thank you."
At the top of my lungs, again and again.
I call out to my precious loved one.
Is my voice reaching you?
In this world that always changes, human warmth never does.
I'm certain I sensed the presence of the one that I hold dear.
～♪
Next Time
His heart filled with unavoidable
emotions, Chagum walks on.
And on... And on...
Next time, "To Hunter's Hole."
Episode 20
To Hunter's Hole
One man's fate can't be
shouldered by another.
What would you do in his place?